Redhat Kickstart

To use kickstart, you must:

Create a kickstart file.

Create a boot media with the kickstart file or make the kickstart file available on the network.

Make the installation tree available.

Start the kickstart installation.

Kickstart file

A kickstart file is a text file. Get the sample from your first installation /root/anaconda-ks.cfg A sample kickstart file is here

These are the configs I think we will need to use.

ignoredisk --only-use=sda

bootloader --driveorder=sda,hda

install
cdrom
keyboard us

lang en_US

clearpart --drives=sda --all

part /boot --fstype=ext4 --size=1024
part pv.104002 --size=68434


volgroup sysvg --pesize=65536 pv.104002
logvol /home --fstype=ext4 --name=home --vgname=sysvg --size=5120
logvol /opt --fstype=ext4 --name=opt --vgname=sysvg --size=10240
logvol / --fstype=ext4 --name=root --vgname=sysvg --size=5120
logvol swap --name=swap --vgname=sysvg --size=4096
logvol /tmp --fstype=ext4 --name=tmp --vgname=sysvg --size=2048
logvol /usr --fstype=ext4 --name=usr --vgname=sysvg --size=10240
logvol /var --fstype=ext4 --name=var --vgname=sysvg --size=10240

network --bootproto=static --ip=10.0.2.15 --netmask=255.255.255.0 --gateway=10.0.2.254 --nameserver 192.168.2.1,192.168.3.1

reboot 

selinux --disabled

text

timezone --utc America/Chicago

%pre
#!/bin/bash
....... you may write a pre installation script here.

%post

Save the file as ks.cfg and place it at the top level of the cdrom drive that we plan to use.

== Making an installation Boot CDROM

Copy the isolinux/ directory from the DVD to a directory

cp -r /cdrom/isolinux/ /prod/images/images/taqa1a03/ 

Change the permission

cd /prod/images/images/taqa1a03/
chmod u+w isolinux/*

Create the ISO

mkisofs -o file.iso -b isolinux.bin -c boot.cat -no-emul-boot \  
-boot-load-size 4 -boot-info-table -R -J -v -T isolinux/

Making the installation tree available

If you are setting up an installation tree for NFS, FTP, or HTTP installations, you must copy the RELEASE-NOTES files and all files from the RedHat directory on all operating systems ISO images. On Linux and UNIX systems, the following process will properly configure the target directory on your server (repeat for each CD-ROM/ISO image):

    Insert CD-ROM or DVD-ROM.

    mount /media/cdrom

    If you are installing the Server variant, run cp -a /media/cdrom/Server <target-directory>

    If you are installing the Client variant, run cp -a /media/cdrom/Client <target-directory>

    cp /media/cdrom/RELEASE-NOTES* <target-directory> (Installation CD 1 or DVD only)

    cp /media/cdrom/images <target-directory> (Installation CD 1 or DVD only)

    umount /media/cdrom

Installation tree is the same as the cope of Redhat DVD.

NFS based installation

Preparing for an NFS install

For NFS installation it is not necessary to mount the iso image. It is sufficient to make the iso image itself available via NFS. You can do this by moving the iso image or images to the NFS exported directory:

    For DVD:

    mv /location/of/disk/space/RHEL5.iso /publicly/available/directory/

    For CDROMs:

    mv /location/of/disk/space/disk*.iso /publicly/available/directory/

Ensure that the /publicly/available/directory directory is exported via NFS via an entry in /etc/exports.

To export to a specific system:

/publicly/available/directory client.ip.address

To export to all systems use an entry such as:

/publicly/available/directory *

Start the NFS daemon (on a Red Hat Enterprise Linux system, use /sbin/service nfs start). If NFS is already running, reload the configuration file (on a Red Hat Enterprise Linux system use /sbin/service nfs reload).

Be sure to test the NFS share following the directions in the Red Hat Enterprise Linux Deployment Guide. 

Perform the installation

https://access.redhat.com/knowledge/docs/en-US/Red_Hat_Enterprise_Linux/5/html/Installation_Guide/s1-kickstart2-startinginstall.html

System Build Notes

As we are only buying IBM these days, these notes are limited to the installation of IBM P Series systems OR blades.

Racking the system

Depending on the type of the system, either the Vendor or the Unix team is supposed to rack the system.

In case of blades, insert the blade into an empty slot in the bladecentre.

Cabling details

IBM P series systems may be lpared. Please use the following details for networking cabling and VLANs

Each frame need two Management network connections for the two HMCs in house tgprhmc2 and taitc051.

A physical lpar that is scheduled to run European applications will need 10.32.50/24 (front end), 10.32.51/24(bck) and 10.32.60/24 (backup) VLANs. Each VLAN needs 2 connections to two different switch modules in the core network and a NIB-etherchannel will be configured on AIX between them.

A physical lpar that is scheduled to run North American applications will need 10.0.48/24 (front end), 10.0.49/24(bck) and 10.32.60/24 (backup) VLANs. Each VLAN need 2 connections to two different switch modules in the core network and a NIB-etherchannel will be configured on AIX between them.

Each physical lpar need two SAN connections. Both the SAN connections can not be taken out of a dual HBA as that will introduce a single point of failure. Each SAN cable must go through a different switch to the FA. Exception is for the DMX4 which is directly attached.

Power on

With the HMC connections plugged in, turn on the frame. This will activate the Service Processor that controls the IBM hypervisor on each frame and try to register to the HMC. When the frame pops up in the HMC GUI, reset the default passwords to abcd1234 and add them to the HMC. Apply the same password and repeat the steps on the second HMC.

The preferable system name is Server-type-model-SerNo i.e. Server-9117-MMA-1093F0. Some systems may be named with the applications if the whole frame is dedicated to a specific application.

Create the lpars based on the documentation / plan.

Install operating system

Add the system to the console database

vi /prod/images/etc/unix_sys_console

Register the system to the NIM server

 smitty nim 

Open a session to the system console from pgnmsv01

/usr/local/scripts/getconsole hostname

Allocate resources and kick off a network installation

smitty nim_bosinst

Boot the lpar to SMS

Using the HMC or HMC CLI, Activate the lpar and boot it to SMS 

From the system console, Navigate to the network boot configuration

Disable spanning tree protocol from adapter configuration

Configure NIM server and Client addresses.

Initiate a network boot

Continue OS installation

Installing patches on HPUX

Do not use the console to install patches - the console messages will messup the window. Always patch from a ssh session

HPUX standard patch bundles are divided into 3 sets.

QPK1131

HWEnable11i

FEATURE11i

Installing QPK1131 or Quality Pack

Perform configuration backup

Download the patch bundle from HP's website. This needs an HP passport login account.

Download the patches and store it in a central location. At tenneco, we store it under 'taitc118:/prod/images/hpux'

From taitc118, either nfs mount OR scp the file to the target server

cd /prod/images/hpux
scp hpux_11.31_01140520.tgz taitc114:/opt/oracle

Logon to the server on it's console.

telnet taitc114-gsp

Login as Admin. Do not use the console to install patches - the console messages will messup the window. Always patch from a ssh session

Unzip and untar the patches

cd /opt/oracle
gunzip hpux_11.31_01140520.tgz
tar xf hpux_11.31_01140520.tar

Perform a sanity reboot - This is to make sure that the server is working okay as of now. These servers are rebooted very rarely, hence it is a good idea to reboot it once.

shutdown -r -y now

Create the patch depot

cd /opt/oracle
./create_depot_hpux.11.31

Install the patches

export LC_ALL=C.en_US
swinstall -s /opt/oracle/depot

At the menu, use 'space bar' to select all the bundles listed.

Then hit “m” to mark them for installation.

Hit 'tab' to get to the menus

Select Actions

Select Install

Hit 'OK' to install the patches.

Phew ….

After the system has come back up, cleanup the temporary location in this example /opt/oracle

MT-I-Clone-AIX-SR_LV

T(-) Confirm Target UNIX Server is Online and all Required Configs Updated

From NIM server:

ssh $clonesystem

In case you cannot login into $clonesystem, escalate to UNIX team lead.

Check the CPU and memory values against master report : Master Source Host-Cloned Target Host-CPU-Memory Report

prtconf | grep -E "Number Of Processors|Good Memory Size"

In case values do not match, escalate to UNIX team lead.

T(-) Validate that Test data has been cleaned out in preparation for final data sync

Validate that only rootvg and page volume groups are present, expected output:

lsvg

altinst_rootvg
rootvg
[pagevg01 or sanpagevg01] -- only on large database servers: peerdb99, peerdb98, paerdb99, paerdb98

In case you see any other volume groups present on the server, escalate to UNIX team lead.

Check if /etc/filesystems contains any filesystems definitions outside of rootvg

lsvg -l rootvg | awk '{print $7}' | grep "^/" > /tmp/rootfs.txt
cat /etc/filesystems | grep -vp nfs | grep : | cut -d: -f1 | grep "^/" | grep -Ev "/proc|/cdrom" | while read fsname
do
grep -qx "$fsname" /tmp/rootfs.txt
if [ $? -ne 0 ]
then
echo "STOP - filesystem $fsname exists in /etc/filesystems but not in rootvg."
echo "$fsname >> /tmp/fsfix.sh"
fi
done

In case you see any messages with the word “STOP”, escalate to UNIX team lead.

T(0) Stop Source Server OS in Tenneco environment

From NIM server:

ssh $source_system

In case you cannot login into $source_system, escalate to UNIX team lead.

Validate that Oracle database(s) is not running

ps -ef | grep ora_ | grep -v grep

In case you see DB processes are running, escalate to UNIX team lead.

Perform AIX shutdown:

sudo shutdown -F

If on console, wait for the “Halt Completed” message or check HMC for lpar status.

T(0) Validate firewall separation between DRiV and Tenneco

From NIM server:

ssh $clonesystem

In case you cannot login into $clonesystem, escalate to UNIX team lead.

Perform ping test to default gateways:

ping 10.0.48.1
ping 10.32.50.1

If you see any of the following responses, escalate to UNIX team lead.

64 bytes from 10.32.50.1: icmp_seq=0 ttl=255 time=1 ms
64 bytes from 10.32.50.1: icmp_seq=1 ttl=255 time=1 ms

64 bytes from 10.32.50.1: icmp_seq=0 ttl=255 time=1 ms
64 bytes from 10.32.50.1: icmp_seq=1 ttl=255 time=1 ms

T(0) Mount and validate provisioned Storage in DRiV environment

From NIM server:

ssh $clonesystem

In case you cannot login into $clonesystem, escalate to UNIX team lead.

Run cfgmgr to acquire presented luns

cfgmgr -v

Check if all luns are in available state

lsdev -Cc disk | grep -v Available

If you see luns in other state than “Available”, escalate to Unix team lead.

Check if all paths are available

lspath | grep -v Enabled

If you see paths in other state than “Enabled”, escalate to Unix team lead.

Do we have recent disk map file?

ls -l /home/tauxrpt/rpt_config/cutover_file_systems.txt

In case the file does not exist or is more than 3 days old, escalate to Unix lead.

sudo rm /var/tmp/diskmap.imoclone

sudo cat /home/tauxrpt/rpt_config/cutover_file_systems.txt |\
sed -n "/Printing diskmap/,/Done Printing diskmap/p" | egrep "datavg|redovg|binvg|nfsvg|logvg|dgtvg01|dwvg01|edivg|edivg01|erappvg01|hydvg01\
|hypvg01|internalsasvg|nim6vg01|nimvg|orasoftvg|pagevg01|psbivg01|pujmvg|pujmvg01|raid5vg01|sanpagevg01|sapexportvg|sapmedia|sapsoft_V6|softvg01\
|srmvg01|srmvg02|swvg01|tctpvg|testvg01|tmplppvg|transfervg|tsbivg01|veritasvg|zycusvg" > /var/tmp/diskmap.imoclone

for vg in $(awk -F: '{print $NF}' /var/tmp/diskmap.imoclone | sort -u | sort)
do
   echo "Working on ${vg} ... "
   grep ${vg}$ /var/tmp/diskmap.imoclone | awk -F: '{print $2}' > ${vg}.pvids
   disks=$(lspv | grep -wf ${vg}.pvids | awk '{print $1}' | tr "\n" " " )
   echo "Recreating ${vg} using ${disks} ... "
   sudo recreatevg -L/ -Y/ -y ${vg} ${disks}
   if [ ${?} -eq 0 ]
   then
      for fs in $(lsvgfs ${vg} | sort )
      do
         sudo mkdir -p ${fs}
         sudo mount ${fs}
         if [ ${?} -ne 0 ]
         then
            echo "Unable to mount ${newname} -- Fix and proceed "
         fi
      done
   else
      echo "Error running recreatevg ${vg} using ${disks} -- Fix and proceed "
   fi
done

T(0) Re-establish NFS shares on AIX Server

Umount NFS filesystems

df -k | grep : | awk '{print $7}' | sort -r | xargs -n1 sudo umount

Double check

df -k | grep :

Mount NFS filesystems

lsnfsmnt | awk '{if ($(NF-1) == "yes") print $0}' | awk '{print $1}' | sort  | xargs -n1 sudo mount

Migration with NIMADM: Network Install Manager Alternate Disk Migration

I. Prerequisites on NIM master

NIM master level

NIM master must be at the same or higher level than the level being migrated to.

To check the OS level of the NIM master: `oslevel -s`

Example NIM servers: sfldmiax241, cdcvilax118

lpp_source and SPOT level

The selected lpp_source and SPOT must match the AIX level to which you are migrating.

To check existing lpp_source and SPOT: `lsnim|grep 7200`

Example lpp_source: 7200-05-00-2037, Example SPOT: 7200-05-00-2037_spot

bos.alt_disk_install.rte

The same level of bos.alt_disk_install.rte must be installed in the rootvg (on NIM master) and in the SPOT which will be used.

Check on NIM master: `lslpp -l bos.alt_disk_install.rte`

Check in SPOT: `nim -o lslpp -a filesets='bos.alt_disk_install.rte' <spot_name>`

Example output on NIM master

    Fileset                      Level  State      Description
    ----------------------------------------------------------------------------
    Path: /usr/lib/objrepos
    bos.alt_disk_install.rte   7.2.5.0  APPLIED    Alternate Disk Installation Runtime
    Path: /etc/objrepos
    bos.alt_disk_install.rte   7.2.5.0  APPLIED    Alternate Disk Installation Runtime

Free space in vg

In the VG, which will be used for migration, there must be enough free space (about the size of the client's rootvg).

Example: VG name: nimadmvg, Free PPs: 1598 (204544 megabytes)

To check free space in the VG: `lsvg nimadmvg | grep -i free`

rsh

Check if the client can be reached via RSH from NIM master: `rsh <client_name> date`

Ensure the necessary entries in ~/.rhosts file in both client and NIM.

Format of ~/.rhosts:

      sap2212 root      

II. Prerequisites on NIM client

Hardware and firmware levels

The client's hardware and software must be at the required level to support the level that is being migrated to.

Free disk

The client must have a free disk, large enough to clone rootvg.

NFS mount

NIM client must be able to perform NFS mounts and read/write operations.

multibos

The nimadm command is not supported with the multibos command when there is a bos_hd5 logical volume.

LV names

LV names must not be longer than 11 characters (because they will get an alt_ prefix during migration, and AIX limitation is 15 characters for an LV).

TCB (Trusted Computing Base)

If you use disk caching option (-j flag), it does not matter if TCB is turned on or off (usually it is not turned on).

However, if you omit ”-j” flag (NFS read/write), TCB should be turned off. (TCB needs to access file metadata which is not visible over NFS).

Command to check if TCB is enabled/disabled: `odmget -q attribute=TCB_STATE PdAt`

ncargs (Specifies the maximum allowable size of the ARG/ENV list when running exec() subroutines)

Ensure ncargs value is at least 256: `lsattr -El sys0 -a ncargs` (chdev -l sys0 -a ncargs='256')

III. Preparation on NIM client

Create mksysb.

Check filesets, commit: `lppchk -v`, `installp -s` (use `smitty commit` if needed).

Run pre_migration script: `/usr/lpp/bos/pre_migration` (it will show you if anything must be corrected, output is in `/home/pre_migration…`).

Save actual config (mounts, routes, filesystems, interfaces, `lsattr -El sys0`, `vmo -a`, `no -a`, `ioo -a`, …).

Save some config files (/etc/motd, /etc/sendmail.cf, /etc/ssh…) to `/home` (these won't be overwritten and can be restored later).

Example for SSH config:

# ssh -v dummyhost 2>&1 | grep "Reading configuration" (it will show the location of ssh_config: debug1: Reading configuration data /etc/ssh/ssh_config)
# cp -pr <path_to_ssh_dir> /home/pre_migration.<timestamp>/ssh

Free up disk: unmirrorvg, reducevg, bosboot, bootlist.

IV. Migration (on NIM master)

Run the following nimadm command

nimadm -j nimadmvg -c "aix_client" -s "spot" -l "lpp_source" -d "hdisk*" -Y

`-j`: specifies VG on master which will be used for migration (filesystems will be created here and client's data is cached here via rsh).
`-c`: client name
`-s`: SPOT name
`-l`: lpp_source name
`-d`: hdisk name for the alternate root volume group (altinst_rootvg)
`-Y`: agrees to the software license agreements for software that will be installed during the migration.

Example:
nimadm -j nimadmvg -l 7200-05-00-2037 -c sap2212 -s 7200-05-00-2037_spot -d hdisk2 -Y

- Migration logs can be found in `/var/adm/ras/alt_mig` directory. There will be 12 phases after that, and you will get back the prompt. Check if `alt_inst_rootvg` exists on the client and bootlist is set correctly.

V. Post migration checks on the client

Check filesets: `oslevel -s`, `lppchk -v`, `instfix -i | grep ML` (update/correct/commit other software/filesets if needed).

Check config, config files: (`sys0`, `vmo`, tunables: `tuncheck -p -f /etc/tunables/nextboot`) (`maxuproc`: `lsattr -El sys0`, `chdev -l sys0 -a maxuproc=<value>`).

Run post_migration script: `/usr/lpp/bos/post_migration` (it can run for a long time, 5-10 minutes).

Others: mksysb, smtctl, rsh, rootvg mirror.

rsync - Use nonprivileged unix account's ssh password-less login to sync files owned by root/another user

Scenario

server1 has a directory that contains software or data, no necessarily owned by the non-privileged user that a team uses for automating cron jobs etc

The data needs to be replicated to server2

The non-privileged user has “sudo” rights to perform “rsync” on both the servers.

Our Scenario

We have https://storagedocs running on pgunap01 in Lincolnshire.

We would like to host https://storagedocs-dr on pgunap02 server in Interxion.

In order to make sure all documents are syncd, we need to “rsync” the data from pgunap01 to pgunap02.

We use a non-privileged user “sanmontr” to schedule cronjobs i.e. We don't use root or any system account for security reasons.

sanmontr unix account has 'sudo rsync' rights on both pgunap01 and pgunap02.

sanmontr unix account has ssh-password-less login access from pgunap01 to pgunap02.

After much googling and brain picking multiple people here, we got this method that works.

rsync --delete -a ${wikihome}/ --rsync-path="sudo rsync" ${drhost}:${wikihome}/

System build specifications for Other teams

Standard Wintel VM build

Please make a request to the Wintel resource to create a VM for Redhat Linux.

Hello Wintel Team,
Please configure a Virtual Machine with the following characteristics,

Type         : Linux
OS           : ( Mention Redhat Enterprise Linux 6 or 7 64 bit )
Processors   : ( enter the number of procs needed )
Memory       : ( enter the RAM in Gigabytes )
Boot Disk    : 1 * 70G, thin provisioned
Data disk(s) : ( details here )
Virtual NIC  : ( Mention the VLAN or subnet here )
Options      : ( Set Boot options to 10,000 ms)

SAP HANA ESXi Build

BIOS Settings

These settings must be performed by Wintel team.

Task | Description
Enable Intel VT Technology | Enable all BIOS virtualization technologies
Enable CPU Intel Turbo Boost | Allows automatic CPU overclocking (P-States)
Disable QPU Power Management | Static high power for QPI links
Enable Hyperthreading | Double logical CPU cores
Enable execute disable feature | Enable the NX-bit, required for vMotion
Disable node interleaving |
Disable CIE Halt state | Disable Enhance C-States in BIOS
Set Power Management to High Performance | No power saving modes (C-Statues
Disable unused BIOS features | On-board audio, modem, serial ports, etc.

ESXi Host configuration

The following host configuration allows the transfer of host data to the virtual machine.

Using VMware vSphere Client:
Select the host in the vSphere client window. 
Choose the tab "Configuration".
In the list of software options, choose "Advanced Settings".
In "Advanced Settings", choose "Misc".
Scroll down to Misc.GuestLibAllowHostInfo and set the value to 1.

Networking

Use: Virtual Distributed Switches (vDS) to connect all hosts that work together Define port groups that are dedicated to SAP HANA, management and vMotion traffic

Storage

Use dedicated HBAs/SCSI controller for DATA, LOG and ESXi Swap/Scratch partition.

Separate log from data!

Memory

Configure RAM hemisphere mode

Distribute DIMM modules in a way to achieve best performance (hemisphere mode), use fastest DIMM modules available for the selected RAM size

CPU

Populate all available CPU sockets, use glueless NUMA architecture

To avoid Timer Synchronization Issues, use a multi-socket server that ensures NUMA node timer synchronization.

NUMA systems that do not run synchronized will need to synchronize the timers on the hypervisor area, which is very costly”

SAP Monitoring

Enable SAP monitoring on the host → Misc. GuestLibAllowHostInfo and set the value to 1.

Details: http://service.sap.com/sap/support/notes/1409604

Virtual Machine Monitor :- Allow vSphere to choose the best virtual machine monitor based on the CPU and guest operating system combination.

CPU/MMU Virtualization Option = Automatic